>> 在法国的一个偏远角落，
>> In a remote corner of France,
一项堪称国家之最的基础设施工程正在如火如荼地推进。
work is underway on one of the country's most impressive infrastructure projects.
>> >> 是一条路，但这可不是一条普通的路。
>> >> A road, but it's not just any old road.
它拥有法国最长的大桥，沿途风景如画——但问题来了。
It contains France's longest bridge and most beautiful drives, but there's a problem.
有一段还没修完，而且缺的还不是一点点，更要命的是，这个烂尾已经拖了很久很久。
There's a bit missing, quite a big bit in fact, and it's been missing for a very long time.
原因在于，走到今天这一步，远比想象中艰难。
That's because getting to this point has been far from easy.
我们说的"偏远"，
When we say remote,
可不是布列塔尼半岛的某个角落，也不是科西嘉岛的海岸线。
we don't mean a distant part of Brittany or the coast of Corsica.
不，你得先抵达阳光明媚的地中海沿岸，
No, in fact, once you get to the sun-kissed shores of the Mediterranean,
然后继续往前走，非常非常非常远——
keep going for a very, very, very long way,
一直到印度洋，在距法国本土将近九千公里的地方，才能找到留尼旺岛（Reunion）。
here, to the Indian Ocean, where nearly 9,000 km from mainland France, you'll find the island of Reunion.
你可能在想：在这里建造大型基础设施工程，到底有多难？
Now, you might be thinking, how on Earth do you build a mega project here?
这个问题问得好，
And it's a good question
因为这里很可能是全球最难修一条路的地方之一。
because it may be one of the most difficult places in the world to build a road like this.
这就是工程极限被不断突破的故事，
This is what happens when engineering is pushed to its absolute limits
也是在地球上最孤立的角落之一建造超级工程所需要付出的一切。
and what it takes to build a mega builds in one of the most isolated corners of our planet.
好，先上一堂简短的政治课。
Okay, let's start with a quick politics lesson.
根据法兰西第五共和国宪法第一条，
According to Article 1 of the Constitution of the Fifth French Republic,
法国是一个世俗、社会性且——对我们来说最重要的——不可分割的共和国。这究竟意味着什么？
France is a secular, social, and importantly for us, an indivisible republic, which means what exactly?
换句话说，法国就是法国，不管你身处哪里——这里、那里、还是这里、那里，甚至这里。
Well, in other words, France is France, regardless of whether you're here, here, here, here, or even here.
因此，尽管留尼旺岛离南极比离巴黎更近，
So, despite Reunion being closer to the South Pole than to Paris,
它依然是欧盟不可分割的一部分，在法国议会中拥有完整的代表席位。
it's an integral part of the EU and enjoys full representation in the French Parliament.
那这和我们有什么关系呢？
So, why does that matter?
其实说白了，关系不大，除了面子问题——
Well, it doesn't really, except for prestige,
因为这意味着"新海岸公路"（La Nouvelle Route du Littoral）
because this means that La Nouvelle Route du Littoral, or New Coastal Road,
不仅是印度洋在建的最令人叹为观止的基础设施工程之一，
isn't just one of the most impressive infrastructure projects being built in the Indian Ocean,
也是整个法国规模最大的工程之一。
it's also one of the biggest in France.
那到底是一个什么样的工程？
Anyway, what's this all about?
留尼旺岛固然美丽，但这座岛屿的内陆被巨型火山所主宰。
Well, as beautiful as Reunion is, the island is dominated by these vast volcanoes.
正因为内陆几乎无法穿越，
Because of this impossible interior,
大多数城镇散落在岛屿边缘——
most towns and cities are dotted around the island's edge,
比如这里，圣但尼（Saint-Denis），岛屿的首府；还有这里，勒波尔（Le Port），岛屿港口所在地。而要往返于两地之间，
like this one, Saint-Denis, the island's capital, or this one, Le Port, which contains the island's port. To get between the two,
只能走这条路——利托拉尔公路（Route du Littoral），就是那条老路。
you've got to use this, the Route du Littoral, the old one, that is.
建于1959年，它紧贴着峭壁，从海岸线上方蜿蜒而过。
Built in 1959, it tightly hugs the sheer cliffs as it passes above the shoreline.
每天约有八万辆车经过这条路，但问题来了。
About 80,000 vehicles use this road every day, but there's a problem.
猛烈的狂风、暴雨和海浪不断袭击这座岛屿。
Violent winds, rain, and waves battered the island.
我们必须清除所有大面积的东西。
We have to clear away anything with a large surface area.
这意味着阵风时速可达两百公里。
That means gusts of up to 200 km an hour.
这条路虽然至关重要，但开车走在上面，却像是夹在魔鬼与深蓝大海之间进退两难。
As vital as this road is, driving it is like being caught between the devil and the deep blue sea.
这片海域的飓风十分频繁，
Cyclones in this part of the ocean are common,
带来的巨浪和时速高达一百英里的狂风不断冲击着公路，
battering the road with waves and winds of up to 100 mph,
而受苦的不只是路面本身。
and it's not just the road that takes a beating.
风化侵蚀不断啃噬着悬崖壁面，
The elements cause constant erosion to the cliff face,
将巨石碎块轰然砸向路面和过路的车辆行人。
sending rocks and boulders hurtling down onto the road and road users below.
2006年3月24日，一整段悬崖突然崩塌，
On the 24th of March, 2006,
大量岩石倾泻而下，造成两人罹难。
an entire section of the cliff gave way, sending tons of rock onto the highway below and killing two people.
这场悲剧发生后，一个更好的解决方案开始被提上日程。
After this tragedy, work began on a better solution.
第一项任务，是研究岩石从悬崖上滚落的最大距离，
The first job was to study the maximum distance rocks could fall from the cliff
并以此划定安全边界——任何新路都必须建在这条线以外。
and to establish a perimeter that any new road would have to lay beyond.
在此基础上，一个大胆的方案被提了出来：将新的海岸公路推向近海，建在安全水域之上。
From there, an ambitious solution was proposed, a new coastal road pushed safely offshore.
第一段将建在高达17米的防波堤之上，
The first part would sit on top of a dyke up to 17 m high
并覆盖护甲层，以抵御百年一遇的风暴。
and covered in armor to help it resist even a once-in-a-century storm.
之后，路线将潜入悬崖内部，穿越一条隧道，最终抵达圣但尼。
From there, it would dive into the cliff face and make the final entrance to Saint-Denis through a tunnel.
然而，计划很快就脱轨了。
But the plan quickly came off the rails.
早期勘探发现，岩层不适合钻探——
Early tests found that the rock was unsuitable for drilling,
这意味着即便隧道方案可行，施工难度也将极高，造价同样极为昂贵。
meaning that any tunnel, if it was even possible, would be extremely difficult and expensive.
方案几经比较，终于在2011年敲定了最终设计。
A few different options were looked at, and then, in 2011, a final plan was put forward.
说真的，不管有没有路，我其实真的很喜欢留尼旺岛的生活方式。
You know what? Road or no road, I actually really quite like the look of life in Reunion.
不好意思，我平时不会这样——但我真的在想，能不能在那里建一栋梦想中的家园？那会是什么样子？
Sorry, I don't normally do this, but I'm just wondering if I could maybe even build my dream house there. What would that even look like?
我的好伙伴Rayon Design可以帮我实现这个想象。
Well, I can find out thanks to my mates at Rayon Design.
如果你是室内设计师或建筑师，
If you're an interior designer or an architect,
Rayon是一个新一代CAD平台，将彻底改变你的工作体验。
Rayon is a next-generation CAD platform that's going to make your life a dream.
它从早期概念到施工图纸，
It's built to streamline the entire design process
将整个设计流程整合到同一个平台上，全程一站搞定。
from early concept development all the way through to construction documents, all in one place.
与传统CAD工具不同，Rayon让你同时完成精准技术图纸、
Unlike CAD tools, Rayon lets you create precise technical drawings,
精美客户演示与灵感板，
produce stylized client presentations and inspiration boards,
以及实时同步、高效管理的采购计划。
and manage procurement schedules that stay live-synced and efficient.
再也不用为了出一套图纸，同时开着五个不同的软件。
No more juggling five different programs just to produce a single drawing pack.
它甚至还整合了AI。比如说，
It even incorporates AI. For example,
如果你在超过一万个图块的库里找不到需要的CAD图块，
if you can't find the CAD block you need in its library of over 10,000 blocks,
几秒钟内就能自己生成一个。
you can create your own in just seconds.
同样的AI，还能把平面图或剖面图
That same AI can take a floor plan or section
一键转换为3D轴测视图。
and transform it into a 3D axonometric view with just a few clicks.
而且由于Rayon完全基于网页端，
And because Rayon is fully web-based,
你的团队可以实时协作，共享单一数据源，彻底告别版本混乱。
your team can collaborate in real time with a single source of truth model with no version confusion.
现在，趁我继续在留尼旺岛设计梦想家园，
Now, while I carry on designing my dream home in Reunion,
你也点击下方链接，免费试用Rayon吧。
why don't you hit the link below and try Rayon for free today.
好了，先让大家回到视频里来。还想再加几棵棕榈树。
Anyway, for now, I'm going to let you guys get back to the video. Want to add a few more palm trees.
西段同样会建在防波堤上，
The western section of the route would once again be built on a dyke,
但不是钻进地下，而是耸立起这条路的标志性景观——大沙卢普高架桥（Grand Chaloupe Viaduct）。
but instead of disappearing underground, it would rise onto its defining feature, the Grand Chaloupe Viaduct.
大桥全长5.4公里，最远伸入海面300米，
Stretching for 5.4 km and up to 300 m away from the shore,
将成为这条12.5公里线路的核心，建成后也将跻身法国最长大桥之列。
it would form the centerpiece of the 12.5 km route and once complete, would become the longest bridge in France.
好，听起来很厉害。但有一点——
Okay, sounds great. Just one thing.
让我们再仔细看看留尼旺岛。
Let's take another look at Reunion.
在法国最大规模基础设施工程之一的工地上施工已经够难了——
As if building one of France's largest infrastructure projects wasn't enough,
偏偏最近的大陆还在1600公里以外，你该怎么办？那就只能自给自足。
how do you also do that when the nearest continental landmass is over 1,600 km away? Well, you've got to be pretty self-sufficient.
来看看这座大桥。
Let's take a look at that bridge.
岛上新建了两座混凝土工厂，专门负责浇筑结构所需的巨型构件。
Two new concrete factories were created on the island to cast the enormous components for the structure.
大桥采用箱梁设计，
The bridge is a box girder design,
通过拼接一系列预制空心结构来形成桥面跨段。
meaning the spans are created by joining together a series of precast hollow structures.
这些箱体内部布有预应力钢缆，将各段紧紧挤压在一起。
Inside these boxes are prestressed steel cables, which squeeze the different sections together.
整座桥由48根桥墩支撑，
All of that sits on 48 piers,
每根桥墩都经过精心设计，以减小潮汐与涌浪对结构的阻力。
each carefully designed to minimize resistance to the tides and swells of water.
桥墩在路线西端附近预制浇筑，每个结构由两个模块组成。
The piers were cast here, near the western tip of the road. Each structure is made of two blocks.
底部基础高15米，重达4500吨，基底宽23米；
The base, 15 m tall, weighing 4,500 tons and featuring a 23-m wide foundation.
其上为墩帽，高度介于9至21米之间。
On top of that, the pier head, measuring between 9 and 21 m.
要将这些混凝土巨物运到施工现场，需要一件特殊的装备。
To transport these concrete giants to the work sites, a special piece of equipment was needed.
认识一下——祖里特（Zurit）。
Say hello to Zurit.
整个项目的其他物资都尽量就近取材，唯独这件例外。
While everything else for this project was sourced as close as possible, this was the exception.
这艘专门制造的驳船来自波兰，大小相当于一个足球场，
Constructed in Poland, this specially designed barge is the size of a football pitch
船上配备混凝土搅拌设备和一台能起吊巨型桥墩的门式起重机。
and contains a concrete mixing facility and gantry capable of lifting the enormous pier sections.
基础构件一件一件地运出去。
One at a time, foundations are sailed out.
就位之后，祖里特的机组人员——像八爪鱼一样——将八条钢腿插入海床，稳固船体。
Once in position, Zurit's crew, for octopus, plants eight steel legs into the seabed to provide stability.
桥墩基础随后被精确放入指定位置。
The foundations are then precisely lowered into place.
落入海床之后，液压千斤顶将结构顶起40厘米，
Once on the sea floor, jacks raise the structure up 40 cm,
再向底板下方的袋体注入混凝土。
allowing concrete to be injected into sacks beneath the base plates.
安装全部48根桥墩，整整耗时四年。
It took 4 years to install all 48 piers.
安装完毕后，架桥机登场，将箱梁逐一安装到位。
Once in place, a beam launcher was used to install the box girders.
它站立在桥墩上，同时在两侧各放置一片梁段，保持平衡。
Standing on a pier, it picks up deck pieces and installs them either side on a pier,
two at a time to maintain balance.
完成两个跨段大约需要一个月，
It takes a month to complete two spans,
之后架桥机移位至下一根桥墩，重复同样的流程。
after which the launcher relocates to the next pier and repeats the process.
2017年，历经四年施工，大沙卢普高架桥正式竣工。
In 2017, after 4 years of work, the Grand Chaloupe Viaduct was complete.
不过，尽管大桥可能是整个项目技术最复杂的部分，
But although the bridge might have been the most technically complex part of the road,
让工程陷入僵局的，却不是它。
that isn't what brought the project to a halt.
问题出在防波堤上。
That came about with the dyke.
这些结构设计精妙，是要将海浪的力量逐步消耗殆尽，
These structures were intricately designed to exhaust the power of the sea
而不是硬碰硬地抵挡。
instead of trying to resist it.
防波堤的建造，先从海床堆砌填方形成堤芯，
Initially, they're created by building up an embankment from the seabed.
再在外部构筑一套精密的护甲防护体系。
From there, they're protected by a sophisticated system of armor.
原理其实很简单：
The principle is simple.
最外层由巨型浇筑混凝土块——护坡混凝土块（Accropode）——组成，直接承受海浪的全部冲击力。
The outer layer is formed of huge cast concrete boulders known as Accropodes.
它们是抵挡汹涌海浪的第一道防线。
They take the full force of ocean swells.
之后，海水被迫穿越一层又一层越来越细密的岩石，
From there, water is forced through layers of smaller and smaller rocks,
形成一道密度递增的迷宫，将波浪的能量层层消耗殆尽。
creating an increasingly dense maze, which zaps the energy from the wave.
效果很好，就是有一个问题：需要大量的岩石。
It's effective, but there's just one thing. It needs a lot of rock.
为了解决这个问题，项目方提出在两处新开采石场——
To solve that problem, the project owners proposed opening two new quarries,
布兰白（Bois Blanc）和圣卢（Saint-Leu）。
here at Bois Blanc and here at Saint-Leu.
这两处采石场本应绰绰有余，
These two sites would be more than enough
足以提供完成防波堤所需的约700万立方米岩石。
to supply the estimated 7 million cubic meters of rock needed to complete the dyke.
但麻烦就在这时来了。公众对采石场的强烈反对席卷而来。
But that's when they ran into trouble. Public backlash against the quarries was intense.
这正是安东尼奥·卡代特（Antonio Cadet）和"别动我们的石头"社区团体所担忧的事。
It's what bothers Antonio Cadet and a community group called Don't Touch Our Rocks.
他们认同修路的必要性，但坚决反对其中一个采石场选址。
They agree the road is necessary, but they're opposed to one of the quarry sites.
当地居民和环保团体纷纷表示反对，
Local residents and environmental groups opposed the plans,
称爆破作业和重型卡车的频繁往来将严重干扰日常生活，
claiming blasting and heavy truck traffic would disrupt daily life,
产生大量灰尘和噪音，并威胁到附近居民区和生态敏感地带。
generate dust and noise, and threaten sensitive ecosystems close to homes and habitats.
你看这里的风，尘土将会飘散到每一个角落，
With the wind you see here, we're going to have dust everywhere around,
所有人都会受到影响，
and all the people are going to be concerned,
尤其是孩子、老人，还有那些本就体弱多病的人。
especially the children and old people and people with already a disease.
先停一下——
Now, before your very eyes,
我们不能低估这个项目背后的环境隐忧。
it's important not to underestimate the environmental concerns of this project.
留尼旺岛能成为令人心旷神怡的度假天堂，不是没有原因的。
Reunion isn't an idyllic island paradise for nothing.
岛屿周边海域孕育着珍贵的珊瑚礁、
The waters around Reunion are home to impeccable coral reefs,
鲸鱼迁徙路线和海豚觅食场所。
whale migration routes, and dolphin feeding grounds.
在这一路段选用高架桥方案，部分原因正是为了尽量减少对自然环境的影响——
Part of the reason the bridge was chosen for this stretch of the route was to minimize the impact on nature,
而对岛屿生态的担忧，并不止于水岸边缘。
and those concerns over the island's ecology don't stop at the water's edge.
在这里开采一座采石场，将造成毁灭性的破坏。
The impacts of opening a quarry here would be devastating.
结果，在2018年，
And sure enough, in 2018,
法院以"将破坏多种受保护物种的栖息地"
on the ground that it would destroy the habitats of several protected species,
为由，裁定禁止新建任何采石场。
the court ruled against any new quarries.
这是一记毁灭性的打击，
It was a devastating blow,
但故事还没有结束。
but it's not the end of the story.
那些巨型火山也不是一无是处——
Those giant volcanoes aren't good for nothing.
它们同样源源不断地为岛上"提供"岩石。
They're also responsible for spraying the island with rocks.
数量之多，
So much, in fact,
以至于多年来，岛上农民
that for years it's been a problem for farmers
一直被土地上遍布的玄武岩巨石所困扰。
whose land is littered with basaltic boulders.
于是，一个妙招应运而生。
So, an ingenious solution was found.
全岛农民
Farmers across the island
受到鼓励，将田间的巨石推到路边，
were encouraged to roll boulders off their land to the roadside,
由专人运往施工现场。
where they were picked up and transported to the construction site.
皆大欢喜——
Win-win.
农民清理了田地，
Farmers cleared their fields,
项目也收集到数百万吨岩石。
and millions of tons of rock was collected for the road.
但这个方案再巧妙，
But as elegant as the solution was,
终究无法满足防波堤护甲层所需的全部岩石用量，
it still couldn't provide all the rubble needed for the road's armor,
而且更糟糕的还在后头。
and there was worse to come.
一项评估发现，所需岩石的数量此前被严重低估了。
In a review, it was discovered that the quantity of rock needed had been massively underestimated.
不是700万立方米，而是需要1200万立方米，才能完成防波堤的建设。
Rather than 7 million cubic meters, 12 million were needed to finish the dike.
就这样，到2019年，项目陷入全面停滞。
And with that, in 2019, the project ground to a halt.
团队研究了从南非运石的方案，
The team looked into sourcing rock from South Africa,
但将岩石横跨两千公里运到留尼旺岛，成本高得令人咋舌。
but the cost of shipping it over 2,000 km to Reunion was astronomical.
这个项目不仅拥有法国最长的大桥，
As well as France's longest bridge,
还解锁了另一项记录——只不过这个记录并不光彩。
the project had also picked up another, less welcome, record.
在仅完成12.4公里中的8公里之后，
With just eight out of 12.4 km constructed,
造价已飙升至逾20亿美元，
the cost had skyrocketed to over 2 billion US dollars,
跻身全球最贵公路之列。
making it one of the most expensive roads in the world.
这个天价造价说来讽刺——
That price tag is bitterly ironic
因为当初在规划阶段，
because back in the planning stage,
将整条线路建成高架桥的方案
the idea of a bridge spanning the entire length of the route
曾被直接否决，理由正是造价太高。
was ruled out because it would be too expensive.
更糟的是，2021年发现，近800块护坡混凝土块安装有误；
To make matters worse, in 2021, it was discovered nearly 800 accropodes were incorrectly installed.
为了纠正这些问题，又不得不拆除
A further 2,500 had to be removed
另外2500块重新定位，光这一项就耗费了2000万欧元。
to reposition the faulty blocks at a cost of 20 million euros.
2022年，留尼旺省议会咬牙拍板，批准将剩余路段以高架桥方案完工，
In 2022, the Reunion Council decided to bite the bullet and approved completing the road as a viaduct,
预计将再增加约7亿欧元的总造价。
potentially adding another 700 million euros to the final bill.
但即便如此，新麻烦接踵而至。
But even that came with complications.
专用驳船"祖里特"在2020年
Zurite, the specialist barge, had been sailed back to Europe in 2020
大桥竣工后已驶回欧洲。
after the bridge was complete.
最后一段路的前期准备工作于2025年底启动，
Preliminary work on the final stretch began at the end of 2025,
高架桥主体施工预计于2027年开工，
and construction of the viaduct is due to begin in 2027
完工日期现已定于2030年。
with a completion date now set for 2030.
与此同时，新公路已完工的路段已投入使用——
In the meantime, the existing parts of the new road are now in use,
只不过中间缺口那段，仍需绕回旧路行驶。
albeit with a detour back onto the old road for the missing stretch.
尽管新海岸公路历经波折，
Despite the shortcomings of the new coastal road,
这座岛屿的工程实力绝不应被低估。
this island's engineering prowess is not to be underestimated.
几十年来，
For decades,
这个法国的偏远角落，一直在比欧洲任何地方都更为恶劣的环境中，缔造一个又一个工程壮举。
this remote corner of France has been building extraordinary feats of engineering
in an environment far more hostile than anywhere in Europe.
三盆地高架桥等工程已经证明，
Projects like the three basins viaduct have shown that this extraordinary island
这座非凡的岛屿能够创造出不仅实用、更令人叹为观止的基础设施。
can create infrastructure that's not just practical, but also beautiful.
但在这里，一旦出了问题，四顾茫然，无处可求援。
But out here, when things go wrong, there's nowhere to turn to.
在如此偏远的地方挑战超级工程，光有工程专业能力还不够—— >> >> 你还必须有那股不管多难都要成功的意志。
Attempting a mega build in such a remote location
is not just about having >> >> engineering expertise.
在如此偏远的地方挑战超级工程，光有工程专业能力还不够—— >> >> 你还必须有那股不管多难都要成功的意志。
You've also got to have that drive to succeed against all the odds.
新海岸公路的故事，并不会抹去留尼旺岛的成就。
The story of the new coastal road doesn't detract from Reunion's record.
它只是说明，这一切成就有多么非凡。
It merely shows how extraordinary it is in the first place.
本期视频由Ryoun Design赞助。
This video was sponsored by Ryoun Design.
别忘了点击下方链接，免费体验Ryoun Design。
Don't forget that you can try Ryoun Design for free using the link below.
一如既往，
And as always, guys,
如果你喜欢这期视频，
if you enjoyed this video
想要更多来自全球最权威建筑视频频道的内容，
and you want to get more from the definitive video channel for construction,
记得订阅B1M。
make sure you subscribe to the B1M.